Guide to the Robert W. Clower Papers, circa 1916-2000 and undated
Robert W. Clower papers circa 1916-2000 and undated
Clower, Robert W.
12.2 Linear Feet 7255 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restrictions apply to some parts of the Robert W. Clower papers.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Robert W. Clower, noted American economist, were received as a gift from Robert W. Clower to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1992-2001.
Biographical Note
1926, Feb. 13 Born in Pullman, Washington (the day Francis Ysidro Edgeworth, the great economist, died), son of F. W. Clower (Professor of Economics at Washington State University) and Mary V. Clower
1943 Graduated from Pullman High School, 52nd out of 54 on academic honors list
1943 Joined army. Thirty-one months of army service
1946, Jan. 7 Married Frances Hepburn (of Aberdeen, Scotland) in Wiesbaden, Germany
1946 Returned to the U.S. and entered Washington State Univ. at Pullman as a freshman in summer session, 1946
1948, April Father died
1948 Graduated B.A. Economics with highest honors from Pullman. Elected Phi Beta Kappa, Phi Kappa Phi scholastic honors. Began teaching economics at Pullman in senior year following the death of his father
1948-1949 Completed MA in Economics at Pullman
1949-1952 Took up residence in Oxford as Rhodes Scholar. Researched under John R. Hicks. Earned Bachelor of Letter, Economics, Oxford University, 1952 (retitled Master of Letters, 1978)
1950-1952 Assistant Tutor, New College, Oxford
1952-1957 Assistant Professor of Economics, Washington State University
1954 Publication of "Price Determination in a Stock-Flow Economy" (with D. W. Bushaw), Economometrica July 1954
1954-1956 Visiting Professor of Economics, University of Punjab, Lahore, West Pakistan
1957 Publication of Introduction to Mathematical Economics with D. W. Bushaw
1958-1964 Chairman, Department of Economics, Northwestern University
1960 Publication of "On the Invariance of the Demand for Cash and Other Assets" with M. L. Burstein, Review of Economic Studies, October, 1960
1961-1962 Director, Economic Survey of Liberia
1962 Visitor to Faculty of Economics, Cambridge University, Michaelmas Term
1963-1966 Editorial Board, The American Economic Review
1965 Publication of "The Keynesian Counter-Revolution: A Theoretical Appraisal," in The Theory of Interest Rates (Hahn and Brechling, eds.)
1965, Summer Visiting Professor of Economics, Makerere College, Kampala, Uganda
1965-1966 John Maynard Keynes Visiting Professor of Economics, University of Essex
1966 Publication of Growth Without Development, an Economic Survey of Liberia
1967, December Publication of "A Reconsideration of the Microfoundations of Monetary Theory" ( Western Economic Journal)
1968-1969 Dean, School of Social Studies and Professor of Economics, University of Essex
1971-1986 Professor of Economics, UCLA
1972 Visiting Professor, Monash University, Summer
1972 Microeconomics, (an intermediate textbook) with J. F. Due
1973, October Visiting Professor, Bank of Italy Research Staff Seminar, Perugia, Italy
1973-1980 Managing Editor, Economic Inquiry
1974, March Visiting Professor, Institute for Advanced Study, Vienna, Austria
1974 and 1977, Fall Visiting Professor, University of Western Ontario
1976 Legally separated from first wife Frances (Hepburn) Clower
1978-1980 Adjunct Professor, Washington State University
1978- Honorary Fellow, Brasenose College, Oxford
1979? Married Georgene (?)
1981-1985 Managing Editor, The American Economic Review
1982, Summer Visiting Professor, University of Canterbury (Christchurch, N.Z.)
1985, March Visiting Professor, University of Siena
1985, Spring Benedict Distinguished Visiting Professor, Carleton College
1986- Hugh C. Lane Professor of Economic Theory, University of South Carolina
1987, June Visiting Professor, University of Orleans (France)
1987- Professor Emeritus, UCLA
1999, Feb. 24 Death of first wife Frances Hepburn Clower
Collection Overview
Most of the Clower papers are professional correspondence covering his entire professional career from 1949 to 1999. The professional correspondence includes recommendations for jobs, promotion and tenure letters, referee reports, invitations, a few clippings, and photographs. The collection also includes manuscript drafts and manuscript fragments of his writings and the writings of other colleagues; course materials, including lecture notes, syllabi, coursepaks, student papers, reading lists, exams, two cassettes, and course grades; printed materials such as articles, journals, and one bound typescript of a book.
Topics covered in the collection include monetary theory, price theory, price determination, disequilibrium, stock-flow analysis, Keynesian economics, macroeconomics, Say's Law, banking, mathematical economics, and the teaching of economics. The collection does not contain a complete set of drafts of Clower's writings. Many of the writings are untitled typescripts and fragments of notes; thus, the researcher may need to identify some writings.
The professional correspondence includes many prominent names of 20th century economics: Milton Friedman, John R. Hicks, Peter Howitt, Arjo Klamer, David Laidler, Axel Leijonhufvud, Don Patinkin, Joan Robinson, Paul Samuelson, and others. Duke University faculty are represented in the Clower papers by Craufurd Goodwin, Neil DeMarchi, and Roy Weintraub. Also included are:
Moses Abramowitz
Jess Benhabib
Clive Bull
David Colander
Paul Davidson
Frank Hahn
John Haltiwanger
Tom Hazlett
Roger Kormendi
Larry Kotlikoff
Robert Solow
Sir Alan Walters
Some writings included in the collection are:
On the Microdynamics of Price Determination in N-Seller Markets, 1956, (published 1958). The collection includes the "master copy" of the paper.
Introduction to Mathematical Economics with D. W. Bushaw (1957). The collection includes a bound typescript of the book.
Stock-Flow Analysis, published 1968. The collection contains the "master copy" of this paper.
The Coordination of Economic Activities ( American Economic Review, 1975.) The collection contains notes for this paper.
Keynes and the Classics Revisited, published 1988.
There are several untitled typescripts and groups of notes on the following topics:
Price theory, price determination, and disequilibrium
Keynes and Keynesian economics
Monetary theory
Say's Law
"The Keynesian Counter-Revolution: A Theoretical Appraisal" (1965), perhaps Clower's most influential paper, does not appear to be in the collection. Reprinted in his own collection of readings in Monetary Theory (1969), drafts of this paper may appear under a different title or in folders on monetary theory. The collection does include clearly labeled 1966 typescripts and notes for the book on monetary theory.
This unprocessed addition to the collection primarily includes professional correspondence and typescripts of several articles written by Clower. No container list was created. (1991-1998) (400 items) (.80 linear feet) (acc#1999-0352)
This unprocessed addition contains files relating to a 1979 antitrust suit (U.S. vs. Kerkorian), and professional correspondence with colleagues and students, primarily from 1999. No container list was created. (1979-1999) (250 items) (.4 linear feet) (acc#2000-0095)
This unprocessed addition to the collection includes primarily writings by Clower (circa 1600 items, 1952-2000 and undated). Includes copies of his 1952 thesis, copies of published articles and unpublished writings (especially from the 1950s), and lectures. A number of items were written with Peter Howitt of Ohio State University. Also included are a few items of correspondence; materials related to courses taught by Clower, including two electronic documents; a file of curriculum vitae and other biographical information, including one color photograph and two electronic image files; two copies of John Maynard Keynes's THE GENERAL THEORY OF EMPLOYMENT INTEREST AND MONEY annotated by Clower; and a few diplomas and awards. Several files of writings and speeches by Clower's father, the economist F. W. (Fay Walter) Clower, are also included (200 items, circa 1916-circa 1946). The electronic files have been migrated to the electronic records server. No container list for this addition has been created. (1916-2000) (1800 items) (3 linear feet) (acc#2001-0088)
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Clower, Robert W.
Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.)-Faculty
University of South Carolina-Faculty
University of California, Los Angeles-Faculty
College teachers-Correspondence
Economics-History-20th century
Economics-Study and teaching (Higher)-United States
Economists-United States-Correspondence
College teachers-United States
Equilibrium (Economics)
Monetary theory
Say's Law
Keynesian economics
Employment
Banking
Pricing
Contents of Collection
- Professional Correspondence in Alphabetical Order Series (RESTRICTED)
  Letters of reference and letters of promotion and tenure are filed under the name of the subject of the letter. Many letters are also filed under the name of the author or recipient of the letter. There are three sets of correspondence filed alphabetically, as they were received from Professor Clower. Names cited once may have more than one letter within a folder, and the letters are not necessarily together within a folder. Letters of reference are often accompanied by a C.V. Some letters are attached to journal articles or drafts of papers.
  - Professional Correspondence in Alphabetical Order, Subseries One, 1965-1991 (Box 1)
    - A:
      - John T. Addison
    - B:
      - Jess Benhabib,; Clive Bull
    - C:
      - Earlene Craver,; Tom Cooley,; R. Crouch, others, 1969-1986
    - D:
      - Paul Davidson,; Jon Duringer, others 1976-1988
    - E:
      - 1972-1982
    - F/G:
      - 1972-1989
    - H:
      - John Haltiwanger,; Ron Heiner, others, 1975-1990
      - Glenn Harrison, others, 1981-87
      - John Hicks (1966), JRT Hughes (1982), Peter Howitt (1978), Havrilevsky (of Duke) (1978), Tom Hazlett (1983)
    - I:
      - Irvine 1981
    - J:
      - Robert James, 1979, 1981
      - Robert Jones, 1976, 1978-79, 1984, 1986
      - Other letters of reference: 1971, 1974, 1979, 1989
    - K:
      - John Kagel, 1977, 1980
      - Roger Kormendi, 1981, Meier Kohn,; L. Kotlikoff, others
    - L:
      - John R. Lott 1982-1984, Leijonhufvud,; D. Laidler, others, 1978-1984, 1989
      - Others, 1972-1985
    - M:
      - Huston McCulloch,; Craig McCann,; Alvin Marty,; S. Margolis, others, 1975-1983
      - Vivek Moorthy, others, 1979-1989
      - Peter McCabe, others, 1972-1981
    - O:
      - Mack Ott,; Joe Ostrey, others, 1965, 1972-1973, 1978-1979, 1981, 1988
    - P:
      - Angel Palerm, others, 1973-1974, 1976-1978, 1982-1983, 1985
    - Q/R:
      - John Riley, others, 1974-1976, 1978-1981, 1982, 1984
    - S:
      - Robert Sexton,; Southern Economic Association,; Bernt Stigum, others, 1970, 1977, 1987-1990
      - Others: 1972-1987
    - T:
      - Stephen Turnovsky, others, 1968, 1979-1981, 1985
    - U/V:
      - Hal Varian,; K. Velupillai, others, 1974, 1977-1980, 1985-1986, 1991
    - W:
      - Craig West,; Nancy Wulwick,; E. Roy Weintraub,; Alan Walters, others, 1965, 1974-1978, 1980-1983, 1988
    - Y/Z:
      - Warren Young,; Peter Zachar, 1989
  - Professional Correspondence in Alphabetical Order, Subseries Two, 1975-1986 (RESTRICTED)
    - A:
      - Moses Abramowitz, others, 1982-1986
    - B:
      - George Benston, others, 1985
    - A-G:
      - 1982-1985
    - H-O: (Box 2)
      - Peter Howitt,; Frank Hahn,; John Hicks,; Harry Johnson, Larry Kotlikoff,; David Laidler,; Alvin Marty, others, 1975, 1978-1979, 1982-1985
    - S-Z:
      - Paul Samuelson,; E. Roy Weintraub,; Alan Walters, others, 1981-1985
  - Professional Correspondence in Alphabetical Order, Subseries Three, 1982-1986 (RESTRICTED)
    - A-L:
      - Moses Abramowitz,; M. Burstein,; Peter Howitt,; Axel Leijonhufvud,; Glenn Harrison,; David Laidler, and others, 1982-1985
    - M-Z:
      - D. McCloskey,; George Shultz, and others, 1983-1986
- Professional Correspondence by Date Series, 1954-1999 (RESTRICTED)
  Mostly contains professional correspondence organized in folders roughly by date (usually by month or year). Contains restricted or sensitive material such as letters of reference, and correspondence on promotion and tenure. The correspondence also includes referee reports and discussion of Clower's and others' writings. In some cases, typescripts or reprints of papers are attached to correspondence.
  - Correspondence with Don Bushaw about book, Introduction to Mathematical Economics, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Roy Harrod,; Gerald Meier,; Alan Walters,; E. A. Chamberlin, John R. Hicks,; Irene Potter, others, 1957-1959
  - R. Heflebower,; Robert Eisner, and others, 1961-1962
  - M. Burstein,; Cliff Lloyd,; John R. Hicks,; Joan Robinson,; Leijonhufvud, H. Johnson,; Paul Davidson,; Martin Kessler, and others, 1965-1971
  - Dan Benjamin,; Ron Britto,; Clive Bull,; Roger Kormendi,; M. Burstein, D. Laidler, Others 1973-1979
  - Ron Britto,; Bill Brown, others, 1980-1981
  - D. Benjamin,; Michael Bordo, others, 1982-1984
  - Milton Friedman,; Moses Abramowitz,; Arjo Klamer,; Bob Hall, others, 1985
  - David Colander,; Philip Mirowski,; Frank Hahn,; Robert Solow, others, 1986
  - Conferences and professional activities, 1986-1987, 1991
  - Don Patinkin,; Angel Palerm,; JCR Dow,; Alan Walters,; M. Burstein, and others, 1987
  - Mack Ott,; Tom Hazlett,; Paul Davidson,; Roger Kormendi,; Orley Ashenfelter,; Robert Solow,; John R. Hicks, others, Jan.-June 1988
  - John Haltiwanger,; M. Burstein,; L. McKenzie,; W. Allen,; Leijonhufvud,; D. Colander, July-Dec. 1988
  - Roy Weintraub,; W. Barber,; M. Burstein,; S. Fazarri,; John R. Lott,; David Colander,; Richard Day,; John Haltiwanger,; Angel Palerm,; Moses Abramowitz,; Mack Ott,; M. Bordo,; JRT Hughes, others, Jan.-June 1989
  - Jan Kregel,; D. Colander,; Don Patinkin,; M. Burstein,; C. Arnsparger
  - Leijonhufvud,; J. Hey, others, July-Dec. 1989
  - Milton Friedman,; Alan Walters,; J. Hey,; M. Burstein,; Jon Duringer,; David Laidler, others, Jan.-June 1990
  - K. Velupillai,; M. Burstein,; Tom Hazlett,; Huston McCulloch, July-Dec., 1990
  - M. Burstein,; Tom Hazlett, others Jan.-Feb., 1991
  - David Colander,; J. R. T Hughes,; Peter Howitt,; Don Patinkin,; Jon Duringer,; Don Bushaw, others, Mar.-Apr., 1991
  - Arjo Klamer,; Milton Friedman,; Peter Howitt,; Axel Leijonhufvud,; Tom Hazlett, others, May-June, 1991
  - J. R. T Hughes,; Nancy Wulwick,; Don Patinkin,; John Haltiwanger,; Don Bushaw,; Robert Eisner, Others, July-Aug., 1991
  - Meir Kohn,; Peter Howitt,; Don Patinkin,; Axel Leijonhufvud,; JRT Hughes,; Milton Friedman,; John Haltiwanger, Sept.-Oct., 1991
  - Milton Friedman,; Nancy Wulwick, others, Nov.-Dec., 1991
  - Angel Palerm,; Peter Howitt,; Jon Duringer, others, Jan.-Feb., 1991
  - Mostly Southern Economic Association conference organizing, Mar.-Apr., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Peter Howitt,; Nancy Wulwick,; Robert Eisner,; David Colander,; Richard Day,; K. Velupillai,; Ingo Barens, others, May-Aug., 1992
  - Peter Howitt,; Axel Leijonhufvud, others, Sept.-Dec., 1992
  - Peter Howitt,; Robert Solow,; B. Johnson, Jan.-Aug., 1993
  - Jon Duringer,; K. Velupillai,; Don Bushaw, Sept.-Dec., 1993
  - Peter Howitt,; Warren Young,; Arjo Klamer,; Edward Elgar, others, Jan.-Apr., 1994
  - Jon Duringer,; Craig McCann,; Paul Davidson,; Jan Kregel,; K. Velupillai,; Arjo Klamer, others, May-June, 1994
  - Arjo Klamer, others, July-Aug.1994
  - Edward Elgar press,; L. Yeager, on K. Velupillai, on Paul Davidson, others, Sept.-Oct., 1994
  - Mack Ott,; David Colander,; K. Velupillai, others, Nov.-Dec., 1994
  - Paul Davidson,; Peter Howitt,; Leland Yeager, others, Jan.-Feb., 1995
  - Peter Howitt,; Ingo Barens,; Milton Friedman,; Larry Kotlikoff,; P. Arestis,; David Colander, others, Mar.-June, 1995
  - Colin Day,; K. Velupillai,; Ingo Barens, others, July-Aug., 1995
  - Ingo Barens,; K. Velupillai,; Peter Howitt,; Paul Davidson, Sept.-Oct., 1995
  - M. Burstein,; Alan Walters,; Peter Howitt, others, Nov.-Dec., 1995
  - K. Velupillai, others, 1996
  - David Laidler,; D. McCloskey, others, 1997
  - Peter Howitt,; Leijonhufvud,; Paul Davidson, others, Apr. 1998-Feb. 1999
  - Unsigned correspondence to and from Clower, undated
- Professional Correspondence by Name Series (RESTRICTED)
  Chiefly correspondence to Clower, sometimes with drafts and other notes attached; arranged in alphabetical order by last name.
  - Oscar Brookins, Feb., 1978-June, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Clive Bull, 1979, 1980, 1983
  - Milton Friedman, 1999, 1972
  - Gary Galles, 1980 (two folders)
  - Raymond Guarnieri, 1973, 1975
  - Sir John Hicks, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Sir John Hicks, Feb., 1966 to April, 1989
  - Peter Howitt, Nov., 1992 to Jan., 1995
  - Cliff Lloyd, correspondence, 1959
  - Don Patinkin, typescripts and correspondence:
    - Never-published paper on monetary and value theory Sept., 1959
    - Correspondence, May 1979
    - Correspondence, 1958-1959 on money paper, leading to symposium in 1960 in Review of Economic Studies
  - Joan Robinson, June 1968, Jan. 1970, July 1976, and a reminiscence in 1991
- Biographical Material Series, 1959-1992
  Correspondence, clippings, photographs, curriculum vitae, and other materials that relate to Clower's personal and professional life. Arranged in random order, as received.
  - Clippings, photographs, C.V.s, and correspondence, Feb. 1964-Nov. 1984 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, C.V.s, clippings, 1959-1992., Includes family tree from 1959, and Federal Reserve conference material from 1986
- Writings Series, 1949-1999 and undated
  Handwritten notes, typescripts, printed articles, and book drafts mostly by Clower and some by others. Note that some writings, particularly writings by others, are included in the Professional Correspondence series when journal articles or drafts of articles are attached to correspondence.
  Many folders contain writings on various topics, in random order as originally received. Many of the writings are fragments, are untitled, or may have a different title in the draft stage than when published; therefore it is difficult to determine all the papers that are not represented in the collection. One of Professor Clower's most important essays, "The Keynesian Counter-Revolution: A Theoretical Appraisal" (1965), does not appear to be represented.
  The Writings Series is organized by date of the earliest writing within the folder.
  - Various papers by Clower, 1950, 1960, and undated (Box 4)
    - "Employment and Equilibrium" and several other papers for Economics 300 during Clower's college years, 1950, 1960, and undated
    - "An American Program for Peace in the Present Crisis," undated
    - "The Theory of Capital and Interest: A Restatement," undated
    - "Some Views on University Education in Pakistan," undated
    - Correspondence on an empirical study of consumer behavior, 1960
    - "Towards a General Theory of Price Determination," undated
    - "A Suggestion for Generalizing the Pure Theory of Production," undated
    - "Monopolistic Competition and Price Determination," undated
    - "Keynesian, Classical, and Stock-Flow Analysis," undated
  - "Fundamentals of the Development of the Labor Movement in Japan to 1930," 1954
  - "Fundamentals of the Development of the Labor Movement in Russia," 1954
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes on cash-in-advance, inflation, distribution of wealth, 1955 and undated
  - Various writings by Clower, 1956-1968 and undated
    - "On the Microdynamics of Price Determination in N-Seller Markets," 1956
    - "Perspectives on Twentieth Century Economic Theory: Comment"
    - Final Report of the On-site preliminary study of the economy of Liberia; conducted by the department of economics of Northwestern University
    - National Science Foundation Research Grant proposal: an empirical analysis of American Economic Development with Special Reference to the Great Depression, 1869-1896
    - "Barter Exchange and Monetary Theory"
    - "Stock-Flow Analysis"
    - "The Problem of Industrial Depression in the United States"
    - "An Essay on the Empirical Implications of the Concept of Aggregate Supply," 1949
    - "Towards a Unified Theory of Market Mechanisms," 1956
    - "The Permanent Income Hypothesis Reconsidered"
    - "The Free Money Fable"
    - Articles on the economy of Liberia
  - Research proposals, 1957, 1968, 1971
  - "Mr. Keynes and the Classics," 1958 and 1986
  - Typescript for paper on price determination, 1959
  - Notes and drafts for book on price theory price determination, 1959, 1961 and undated
  - Banking Study. "The Liberian Banking System," A letter dated April, 1962
  - Papers, notes, and typescript fragments on Keynes, macroeconomics, other topics, 1962-1994 and undated
    - "A Symposium on Monetary Theory," ( The Review of Economic Studies, Vol. XXVIII, No. I)
    - Outline of book with Leijonhufvud on the coordination of economic activities
    - Draft of paper "The Vision of Keynes," Mar., 1994 by Clower
    - Draft of paper "The Keynesian Paradigm: and Attempt at Reconstruction," 1971
    - "The Optimality of Money Under Laissez Faire" (unpublished, unsubmitted paper)
    - Transcription of Perugian conference, 1986 or 1987(?)
  - Puerto Rican shipping study, 1965
  - Typescripts and notes for book on monetary theory (1966); other topics
  - Additional typescripts and notes for book on monetary theory (1966); other topics
  - Clower papers, 1966 to 1991
    - "Growth without Development: An Economic Survey of Liberia," 1966
    - "Effective Control Through Coherent Decentralization with Preemptive Goals," 1967
    - "Mathematical Introduction to Price Theory," 1969
    - "Reflections on the Keynesian Perplex,," 1972
    - "Perspectives on Twentieth Century Economic Theory: Comment," 1973
    - "The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity"
    - "The Invisible Hand," 1991
  - Various typescripts and fragments of notes; drafts for macroeconomics book, 1967-1968
  - Pricing and disequilibrium typescript and note fragments, undated (Box 5)
  - "Price Theory -- Notes, false starts, etc."
  - Clower's comments on "Effective Demand Failures," paper by Grossman, 1973(?)
  - Assets and dividends paper with Smith, 1967(?)
  - Early papers and notes on various topics, 1968-1979 and undated
    - Fundamentals of monetary theory
    - Notes on possible papers
    - Outline of book Thinking Economically
    - Notes for lectures on pricing and disequilibrium, Jan. 1979
  - Papers and notes on Keynes and Marshall, truth in economics, and other topics 1971-1991 and undated
  - Early papers and notes on various topics, 1972 and undated
  - Miscellaneous notes and paper fragments, 1973-1991 and undated on the General Theory, other topics
  - "A Bayesian Approach to Price Theory," 1973
  - Notes and correspondence for conference in Perugia, Italy, Oct. 1973
  - Drafts for paper on Say's Principle with Leijonhufvud, 1974 and undated
  - Notes and drafts for book Mathematical Introduction to Price Theory, undated
  - Notes and correspondence for paper "The Optimal Timing of Transactions," American Economic Review, May 1974